Rym: It's Thursday, December 12th, 2024.
Rym: I'm Rym.
Scott: I'm Scott.
Rym: And this is GeekNights.
Rym: Tonight, we're gonna be talking about knives.
Rym: Oh yeah.
Rym: Let's do this.
Rym: So, uh, I found something recently, like really recently, that I forgot about.
Rym: And so, back when Zappos was a thing, like, it existed.
Scott: It is.
Scott: It's still a thing.
Rym: Not really.
Rym: Go look at their selection.
Rym: Like, they stopped using them a long, long time ago.
Rym: Uh, but there was an ancient time, like when we lived in Beacon, in the early days of living here, I bought all my shoes there.
Rym: Like 100% of them.
Scott: That was before Amazon bought them.
Rym: Yup.
Scott: And before the CEO died of too much drugs.
Rym: And I remember the moment I stopped using them- Hey!
Scott: What do you mean?
Scott: their selection's bad?
Scott: They got the Christmas Crocs right here.
Rym: Let me see.
Rym: Special edition.
Rym: Like four years ago, I went there- Squid Game Crocs.
Rym: Okay, let's see if they have the shoes I buy.
Rym: They do not have the Nikes that I run with.
Rym: Let's see if they have the old Nikes I used to run with.
Rym: They do not have those shoes either.
Rym: Anyway, they went way downhill a long time ago.
Rym: At least for me, as a sports shoe buying person.
Rym: But, at some point, between 2009 and 2010, I bought two pairs of sneakers on Zappos.
Rym: One of those pairs I wore until they wore out and I threw them away.
Rym: And the other pair, when they arrived, they were like- I bought shoes back when you and I were talking about this.
Rym: I think we talked about it in GeekNights.
Rym: I wanted to get shoes to leave at the office.
Rym: Like, just nice hush puppies.
Rym: They're like comfortable and don't get beat up.
Rym: And then I have other shoes that I wear like out in the street.
Rym: And when I got them, they looked cool.
Rym: But they had a weird- like you had to lace them a weird way.
Rym: And there was like instructions in the box.
Rym: And I was like, "Eh, I don't want to deal with this right
Rym: now.".
Rym: So I put them back in the box and left them in the closet.
Rym: I forgot about that until a few weeks ago.
Rym: And I found these shoes.
Rym: Unused, unworn, unlaced.
Rym: So I laced them up.
Rym: I figured out the complicated lacing scheme.
Rym: And it wasn't that complicated.
Rym: It took about twice as long as like normally lacing shoes.
Rym: Because you have to like do it in the opposite direction.
Rym: But it worked fine.
Rym: And these shoes looked good.
Rym: So I wore them to work.
Rym: And people complimented me on my shoes.
Rym: Which is something that is, other than wearing Vibrams, has never happened in my life.
Rym: People were like, "Why don't you give me
Rym: shoes?".
Scott: Maybe since they're old, maybe some sneaker collecting people are like,
Scott: "Whoa."
Scott: Ah!
Rym: So then, in the evening, one of my feet hurts.
Rym: And not in the like, the normal "breaking in" of a shoe.
Rym: Which has nothing to do with breaking in a shoe.
Rym: And has more to do with callus patterns than people's feet.
Rym: But it was a different pain.
Rym: It was the kind of pain you get from a sports injury.
Rym: So I suspected the shoes immediately.
Rym: Because the last time I had a foot problem in my life was because I wore the same shoes for like 800 miles of running.
Rym: And I got plantar fursitis.
Rym: I went to a doctor.
Rym: And the doctor said, "How long have you had your current running
Rym: shoes?".
Rym: And he interrupted me and said, "Buy new shoes.
Rym: That'll fix your problem.
Rym: What's wrong with
Rym: you?".
Rym: So, I wore them a little bit one more time to confirm.
Rym: And I figured out the problem.
Rym: So I'm going to give these shoes away or maybe sell them because they're like decade old hush puppies that apparently people like to look up.
Rym: They are too short top-wise.
Rym: And I have a very pronounced arch because I'm athletic.
Rym: Like I have a strong arch.
Rym: Like I run a lot.
Rym: And if you compress the arch of the foot of someone who has a strong arch and runs and is an athlete in any way with their feet that can actually cause significant sports injuries because it prevents the proper flexing of the foot.
Scott: Now if you squeeze any part of your body out of shape it's going to mess you up.
Scott: It's like your body, you know, it's like come on there's just common sense.
Rym: But if you're not athletic and have flat feet, like messed up feet then it might not be a problem.
Rym: So basically I can't wear these shoes so I got to get rid of them.
Rym: So I have some shoes from 2009.
Scott: Even Zappos ain't going to take a return that late.
Rym: Next I should send my Nintendo Power survey back because I found one of those Your subscription card for the Nintendo Power.
Rym: I have the subscription card that we got back when we first subscribed to Nintendo Power and called the Pro Wrestling Outline card.
Rym: So in the news kind of a big news happened and a lot happened since then.
Rym: I'm sure you've read about it.
Scott: if you don't know what we're talking about go read real news sites If you don't read enough normal news to even know this kind of news and you listen to GeekNights you need to be reading normal news before you spend time listening to GeekNights.
Rym: The CEO of a healthcare company was assassinated in Midtown Manhattan recently if you didn't see the news and it was a big enough deal.
Rym: I work in Midtown.
Rym: it happened kind of near my office and we got security alerts and everybody freaked out.
Rym: and what was interesting immediately is I discovered at that moment who in my collected work-o-sphere that Rym's WorkSona pretends to be a professional in reads the internet at all versus people who don't because there were three waves of people.
Rym: well now I've discovered the true map because there are actually three classes of those people in my work-o-sphere.
Rym: class one had no idea this happened oblivious to the world class.
Rym: two heard it happened and assumed it was random street violence which not common like that doesn't really happen especially in Midtown.
Scott: I mean I assumed that for like a fraction of a second while I was reading.
Scott: I was like read words, read words, read words.
Scott: oh read more words.
Rym: your mind puts the story together as you go.
Scott: if you stop reading after just three words.
Scott: yeah I would have thought.
Rym: third group of people read words on the internet and realized it wasn't like.
Rym: it was a big deal story and not a random shooting story.
Scott: yeah basically when I was reading the words my initial thought was oh everyone's gonna think it was an assassin who was mad about not getting their healthcare coverage but it's probably something else.
Scott: nope actually that's absolutely what it is 100% okay.
Scott: so the moment I realized it was similar to 9/11 where I was like oh people are gonna say it's terrorism.
Scott: it was terrorism.
Rym: yups but for me it was specifically when like in the second paragraph of the article like that popped up that I read and I was like kinda chatting with a co-worker who was reading the same article and I noticed something interesting.
Rym: I noticed that nobody reported hearing a gunshot and the next line was someone claimed the gun appeared to have a silencer.
Rym: now that kind of claim in breaking news is often wrong just like when there's a mass shooting.
Rym: almost everyone says eyewitnesses are super unreliable and nobody knows what a fucking silencer looks like.
Scott: they know what one looks like in a Hollywood movie.
Scott: yup a little black cylinder stuck at the end of a gun where you think there should be nothing.
Rym: yup and it makes a little like *boop* noise when you shoot it which is not how silencers work normally.
Rym: but being an internet person who's played Counter Strike and knows things that triggered something for me because I immediately realized if it is true that no one heard a gunshot silencer or no silencer that implies the shooter used subsonic ammunition.
Rym: so that's the only way to make a gun quiet and subsonic ammunition is already a thing that most people have never heard of and already this is sounding more like someone who knew what they were doing.
Rym: and then I saw that little video that was making the rounds and it was like a movie style assassination like the calmly walking forward firing a gun from a dark corner.
Rym: obviously was an assassination.
Rym: and then pretty soon after the police were like especially when the shell casings had those three words written on them which Amazon has now banned from any listings.
Scott: and then I heard some conspiracy theories that were like somebody was trying to this guy, this CEO was less evil than the other health insurance CEOs.
Scott: they wanted to shut him up so they faked this to make it look like a disgruntled and it's like that's conspiracy talk.
Scott: that's obviously not true.
Rym: read the news about the details of what happened what I actually want to talk about and again I want to preface this with something very important.
Rym: I and GeekNights are not advocating anything.
Rym: we are simply reporting on news that is being reported because there is a fascinating phenomenon happening and this isn't just an internet thing.
Rym: the reaction from a wide range of people in real life online, not just in nerd and edgelord circles but like in regular places that regular people go range from indifference to celebration.
Rym: more people even republicans yep, like at PAX.
Rym: I overheard strangers talking about this in a neutral to positive manner in like random conversations.
Rym: I overheard around work outside, on trains like people are talking about it and again the reactions are ranging from indifferent to positive and the media are covering this sort of directly as like this is an outrage, reward, assassination, whatever.
Scott: it's a big deal.
Rym: but if you look at like any press that isn't like the CNN, MSNBC Fox News type stuff there's a lot of articles pointing out that people seem to be celebrating this and this is everywhere now, that implies something important.
Rym: again I'm not saying assassinate people, what I'm saying is it is very telling that in the year 2024, considering the state of the world, the state of the United States the state of healthcare, the anger everywhere our political situation
Scott: that
Rym: there is a class of people who are extremely terrified that this happened and there is a broader class of people across a wide range of the social sphere that are indifferent to positive on this and it's only escalated.
Scott: and yet they voted for someone who's on the side of the guy who got killed.
Rym: yup, but like GoFundMe's appeared that got shut down.
Rym: so much merch for Luigi.
Rym: the character was sold that like it's sold out everywhere Amazon has been constantly taking down like pro assassination t-shirts.
Rym: they're like.
Rym: read the news about this.
Scott: I think yesterday we should make some.
Scott: I can't remember the guy's name anymore the guy who shot the start of World War I whatever.
Scott: it is Archduke Ferdinand.
Rym: actually, I should link to something because the shooting of Archduke Ferdinand how do you think it went down, like from memory?
Rym: I'm just curious, like what do you?
Scott: I mean?
Scott: all I remember was they showed a photo of a car right, but obviously it wasn't a sniper like JFK because it was 19 whatever the fuck.
Scott: so 14 something like that, right since there's no video of it it's not like they had an iPhone down in the streets of Austria whatever.
Scott: I always had just imagined that someone just like walked up to the car and shot him and ran away.
Rym: so it's actually a lot crazier than that.
Rym: there were a bunch of conspirators several of them.
Rym: part of the reason they did it was that they perceived the world as going to shit and they were worried about big wars and injustice and whatever.
Rym: but also they were dying of tuberculosis and figured why not do something good with the tiny bit of my life that I have left similar to Luigi here who had been suffering from illness.
Rym: yep insurance company clearly wouldn't pay for not to put a really big sort of downer serious note on GeekNights before we get into a fun chat about knives and interstellar 5555. but this feels like a symptom of a widespread upheaval that I think we're in the middle of World War 3 just like in the 20s we were at the beginning of World War 2.
Rym: I think a lot of shit is coming.
Scott: I mean clearly a lot of shit is coming but you know Rym is always the person who freaks out over every single news and then the next day the sun rises like what?
Scott: I'm not going to say it's World War 3 until it's World War 3.
Rym: I mean I called that Russia was invading Ukraine and I was deeply right about that.
Rym: well in advance.
Scott: ok and?
Scott: yeah
Rym: I mean I'm not saying I can do anything about it but I think the fact that the
Scott: media
Rym: and like the zeitgeist of America expected outrage from the population at this assassination and instead the result was what it was really says a lot about the anger and the societal problems that are escalating in America.
Rym: that the every American no matter what they think they believe politically has been so harmed by the insurance and medical industry in the United States a country that spends the most on healthcare over any other country in the world and yet provides honestly not great care for a lot of Americans.
Scott: this is the problem right.
Scott: so the media even the good normal truth telling media is they're afraid to like talk positively about an assassin and rightly so.
Scott: we don't want assassinations.
Scott: that's not the right way to solve these problems.
Scott: we would rather solve them with the justice system that would be hopefully functioning properly.
Scott: that would lead to a much more healthy society.
Scott: just like war sucks we should try to solve issues no matter how dire they are with diplomacy first but yet when they strongly condemn this kind of violence in the normal media and they don't want to talk positively about it in any way.
Scott: but when health insurance companies murder people when cars murder people when someone with a factory that pollutes and gives cancer to a whole town murders people they don't treat those murderers, mass murderers the same way that they treat Luigi or someone who shoots up a school.
Rym: there weren't manhunts like this for the 16 shootings that happened other than that one in a similar period of time.
Scott: so when a company murders people, a whole town of people indirectly with its pollution or gives cancer to a zillion people with its products that are tainted or someone selling poisoned food gives a bunch of people E. coli the media the truth telling media that didn't lie about anything.
Scott: they should be treating those corporate executives the way that Luigi is being treated by them now and in fact even worse because they are mass murderers.
Scott: and that's exactly why people are on the Luigi side here.
Scott: because even though most people don't look to say someone who's killed indirectly by climate change or someone who's killed indirectly by various means the healthcare murdering executives everyone can draw a direct line of.
Scott: I was at the hospital and I was dying and this company said just die.
Scott: there's not the ambiguity of the separation of.
Scott: I died from this thing that was far away from pick an evil CEO I guess oil company executive.
Scott: it's like when a car hits you.
Scott: it's kind of hard to make that connection to like Exxon CEO even though they did kill you indirectly or Ford CEO or whatever.
Scott: but when the hospital is trying to save you, you don't play in the hospital the doctor is trying to treat you and you end up telling the doctor no don't help me I have no money.
Scott: people have this direct lived experience and they can line it up and say that's the guys at fault and that's why they were targeted.
Scott: and that's why you're not going to see someone who is hit by a car trying to assassinate Ellen Musk if they were killed by a Tesla for example.
Rym: because American healthcare even people who have good insurance have a really bad time with American healthcare it is I would say it's shocking but it's not shocking that the richest country in the world has such a crappy healthcare system.
Rym: it's not actually shocking.
Rym: what's the old meme you see in military analyst circles?
Rym: country X is about to find out why Americans don't have healthcare
Scott: and the thing that baffles me the most we could talk about it for the whole episode but this will be the last thing I say about it is that it's clearly popular to get other than the people who run and work for these insurance companies.
Scott: it's very popular amongst everyone else to eliminate private health insurance and just have the same free health insurance that every other country has thanks to the internet we know about.
Scott: without the internet, Americans wouldn't know about that except for a few who have been to other countries.
Scott: I only heard rumors about that.
Rym: America is literally the only industrialized country on earth that doesn't have public healthcare right, and so once we learned about that we said that's obviously better, why don't we have that?
Scott: so now there's a bunch of people that know about it and want it and advocate for it but neither of the two major political parties in the United States put that at the forefront of their platforms.
Rym: so the Democrats did when we passed Obamacare.
Scott: no, they said Bernie was coming through and they're like, no Bernie, we don't want you.
Rym: so how that went down and I'm saying this only because it's literally true.
Scott: Kamala Harris could have just come out and been like, I'm for 100%.
Scott: eliminate all private health, she didn't do that.
Scott: Joe Biden, as progressive as he was, most progressive president ever did not.
Scott: openly every time he talked about healthcare he could have said, I advocate eliminating all private insurance companies, destroyed them put them out of business.
Scott: he never said that they could have said that they didn't and Republicans obviously don't say that.
Rym: so when that was said when the ACA was being put together and passed and when it was said when Hillary Clinton way back in the day when Bill was president she did say it way back in the day.
Rym: but in both cases in polling among voters it was deeply unpopular because people don't understand it and got mad about it.
Rym: similar to how the Affordable Care Act is very popular.
Rym: yet if you ask voters if they support it a majority of them will say no depending on how you ask the question.
Scott: the point is you could just fucking do it if either party actually did it.
Rym: well what do you mean?
Rym: actually did it?
Rym: doing it required passing the filibuster right, we're not talking about this.
Scott: the point is you can the Republicans could do it and then you know what.
Scott: how would Democrats ever win again except they wouldn't?
Rym: well obviously because they don't want there to be good healthcare I'm just saying.
Scott: but there are other countries with evil dictators who put forth free healthcare for the people to maintain their popularity.
Scott: so even in the United States there's no one smart enough to do that.
Rym: well thus the fundamental divide.
Rym: the Republicans won't do it on principle because they're just evil as a party just like they won't put forth a lot of things.
Rym: it would be obvious wins for them to cement their power.
Rym: they just don't.
Rym: the Democrats actually had enough votes to put single payer in the original ACA.
Rym: the problem is they didn't have enough votes to also pass the filibuster with single payer.
Rym: I'm just saying they had enough votes to do one but not both and they barely had enough to do even the first one because no Republican would vote for it.
Scott: clearly there's support for it.
Rym: well there is until you poll people and people are stupid and they say they'll vote against it.
Scott: just ignore that, don't worry about that.
Rym: but again, how do you get people to vote for it if you just go out and end your campaign?
Scott: be pro-Luigi not pro-assassination but pro-insurance companies.
Scott: suck put your campaign on that at the forefront of your campaign.
Scott: talk about evil corporations.
Scott: don't take corporate money.
Scott: don't have lobbyists anything.
Scott: lobbyists come to you with.
Scott: do the opposite.
Scott: that's the one thing that unites the Democrats and the Republicans.
Scott: there's a hate for corporate America hurting the people and if you come out against the corporations you can win an election.
Rym: Republicans won't do that in practice for obvious reasons, but Democrats are tricky because generally people who do that lose their primaries.
Rym: so what you would have to do is not say that somehow win your primary anyway and then start saying it for the general election regardless, I think that is a unifying.
Scott: Luigi has shown that there is a unifying factor.
Scott: there's not a lot of unifying things in this world right now in any country.
Scott: this is a thing that unifies people.
Rym: I think it's because it hurts the US healthcare system.
Scott: it hurts so closely whoever you are, you should jump on that.
Rym: even a really bad person probably has a relative who went bankrupt because of healthcare problems.
Rym: yeah in some other much lighter news a while back it was announced that Intersella 5555 which if you've never seen it holy shit, just Google it and watch it was getting a remaster and a one night only.
Scott: it's not one night only, it's a few nights depending on where you live.
Scott: that's what they originally said but if you go on Fandango you can see it's like 4 or 5 nights.
Scott: there's several screenings but regardless the little trailer they showed at first glance looked amazing like wow, we gotta go see this.
Scott: but then when people looked close they said wait a minute.
Scott: is this trailer just an AI machine learning garbage upscale, they didn't really remaster it properly and that's what the trailer was.
Scott: and so it's like.
Scott: well okay, they did that for the trailer, but is that there was still a question of some lingering doubt, obviously not likely, but still possible that the actual movie you saw in theaters wasn't gonna be like the trailer?
Scott: they just threw out a quick trailer like that and they really did do a remaster somehow knowing the history of the film.
Scott: it was questionable how, but somehow and then of course now it has been confirmed by people who have seen the remaster and reviewed it that no, it really is just a garbage.
Scott: all they did was take whatever they had and run it through a machine learning upscaler and it's garbage.
Scott: and the old DVD is still better.
Rym: yup, there's no reason to go see this.
Rym: the only reason I even remembered is when it was announced.
Rym: I put a reminder in my calendar the day before tickets would go on sale to have figured out by then whether or not it would be worth seeing and obviously I have not bought tickets but this review, I'll link to the review on Anime News Network because they go deep into why there aren't remasters of it and there's a lot of information here and I cannot stress
Scott: it enough.
Scott: it was animated in France in the PAL frame rate and then it was like, so the US releases with NTSC are messed up and it's not like.
Rym: it's on a reel of film somewhere and you know it wasn't even, anyway yup, but if you don't know what this is it's a Leiji Matsumoto animated music video to the entirety.
Scott: Leiji Matsumoto's actual involvement with it is overstated but it is obviously heavily heavily influenced by him and he does have some relationship and it was Toei that did it, like Toei put it together but it's a French animation.
Scott: it's literally one long music video to the Daft Punk album Discovery.
Scott: because the Daft Punk guys, they watched all kinds of Starlock growing up, so they did this on purpose and they just, instead of making music videos, they just made an animation that's as long as the album and then they chopped it up and the album is the only audio you hear and each one every song has a music video, which is effectively one scene of the three minute scene of the movie
Rym: and it tells a
Scott: pretty good
Rym: story for a music video with no dialogue.
Scott: it's an anti-evil record company story, right?
Scott: and it's a pro music story.
Scott: it's an amazing movie, you should see it.
Scott: just don't see this fake 4K non-remaster that they've come out with.
Rym: I remember when we got a copy of it and we showed it to the RIT Anime Club on that big screen.
Rym: that was one of our most packed showings and people, the thing happened.
Rym: that would happen usually only after when we do a marathon and people see all of Cowboy Bebop in one go.
Rym: but when it ended, everyone just sat there in silence mulling it over, and then they all stood up and clapped and it was a good time.
Rym: God, that was back in or when we did that.
Scott: yeah, it's surprisingly old.
Rym: I mean, we were still in college running the RIT Anime Club.
Rym: but anyway, things of the day, even though it's Thursday I got another animation related thing.
Rym: so there is, there's a lot of Star Treks but one of the Star Treks that doesn't have that many episodes was an animated Star Trek that isn't Lower Decks, and it was made a long time ago, like in the 70s on basically zero budget and it's actually pretty good, some of the episodes are pretty good, but what is not well known and not widely seen is that in the 70s they made a 36 second PSA against pollution as a concept and someone took this and it isn't really remastered so much is restored.
Rym: this is probably the highest quality version of this old PSA that exists on Earth because nobody gives a shit about this thing.
Scott: but yeah, old cartoons back in the day for a variety of reasons had these little PSA's.
Rym: but what's sad about it, the more you know is that the moral of it is.
Rym: humans were polluting the planet but then people pointed out that pollution is uncomfortable and sucks.
Rym: and once people realized how bad pollution was, they all stopped doing it.
Rym: and then Kirk's like, yes, all they had to do was realize that pollution sucks and they stopped doing it.
Rym: and here we are in the year 2024. so what do you got?
Scott: So I like a rubber stamp, a rubber stamp is one of those things, you know there's some people who are like way into rubber stamps but it's like one of those things.
Scott: that's like I really enjoy a rubber stamp but it's like I can't be going out buying rubber stamps and getting cool ink pads and shit like that because what the heck am I gonna stamp right?
Scott: That's not a thing I'm actually gonna use.
Scott: so I just enjoy the art, the craft of rubber stamps right?
Scott: without actually involving myself.
Scott: but I came across this rubber stamp set that I'm not going to buy.
Scott: that contains 16 separate stamps, it is called Lord of Maps and all of the stamps resemble the features that you will see on maps drawn by J.R.R.
Scott: Tolkien in Lord of the Rings books, you've got, you know mountain, differently angled mountain, big mountain, tree single tree, hill, bunch of trees, lake you know, those kind of things volcano with smoke coming out.
Rym: these look so good.
Scott: and so if you had these stamps and you had some nice ink available to you to use with the stamps, you could combine them intelligently to produce a J.R.R.
Scott: Tolkien style map you know, to look like, I guess it wouldn't be middle earth but I guess you tried to copy the map exactly, but you could make, I don't know side earth, top earth bottom earth, behind earth you know, outside earth, inside earth something like that.
Scott: and so if you're a map making type person maybe you're making some RPG zines or just a map for your little campaign that's token-esque or anything like that, these stamps might come in handy and they're only 40 bucks.
Scott: and then you got to buy ink yourself which you could get some high quality ink pad somewhere, I don't know what's good.
Rym: That's not a bad deal because in the year 1994 I purchased a floppy disk that had for 70 US dollars 70, 1994 US dollars for a program called Campaign Cartographer that was just to make maps that kind of look like this for D&D games and I didn't have a good way to print them and
Scott: so it would be even better if they released.
Scott: you know, like another set, like Lord of Maps 2 then you could really get crazy.
Scott: you know, they could include like little villages or a little river, you know, I guess you had to draw the rivers yourself.
Scott: they're just lines.
Rym: you know what this would be good for?
Rym: Just to put a little tiny map like on envelopes around the holidays that you send to people.
Scott: Sure, that's another good use of stamps.
Scott: Any good uses of rubber stamps.
Rym: The GeekNights panel at PAX Unplugged went well, it'll be on YouTube this weekend.
Rym: I'm mostly done cobbling it all together.
Rym: we will be live at MAGFest with a bunch of lectures, we will be, well I will be live, I doubt Scott will come at Zenkai Con with a bunch of lectures.
Rym: we're very likely going to be live at PAX East and otherwise that's the holidays, we'll see how many shows we do toward the end of the year, but I'm not traveling anywhere, so we'll see.
Scott: How's your book club situation, which you know it was one thing when we didn't do the book club for Tale of Genji because the book was long and difficult to read.
Scott: it's another thing entirely where you've actually chosen a book, but you haven't gone through the effort to actually choose the ISBN number.
Rym: I mean, I was just going to do all of them, but your like weirdly visceral reaction to not wanting to read those books I'm just saying, you know I just disapproved, but I got.
Scott: no you know, the other choice, which I forgot what it was was, you know, more.
Scott: meh, I guess.
Rym: cause I mean, they're not long, I would say just read all of them.
Scott: you choose whatever you chose but you gotta, you have not updated the website, or instructed, given any instruction what is necessary.
Rym: you seemed so displeased that I kind of soured on the whole.
Scott: you didn't do anything, you did just do something.
Rym: yep, I kind of just soured on it because you don't seem to want to read them in the first place.
Rym: I don't feel like it'd be a good episode.
Scott: I mean, you chose the book.
Scott: you gave two choices.
Scott: I picked one.
Rym: I'll do a separate thing on those and I'll just pick a different book for next week.
Scott: you just change what you're picking now, just because I'm meh?
Scott: oh, that's a great power, I'll just I've avoided the two choice situation, now I can just meh your two choices and always get a third choice, okay yeah, I mean, honestly, it'll probably make better episodes.
Rym: if you're not into it, there's no point in doing it.
Scott: hmm, I'll just pick something.
Rym: yep, I'm gonna pick something different.
Scott: the book club has been on hiatus, it's all your fault.
Rym: yeah, that's fine, I've been busy anyway, let's talk about.
Scott: I don't even know when did we pick the book.
Scott: it's been like, a super long time.
Rym: so let's talk about Knives which, loomed.
Rym: it's interesting, when I was a kid like, Cub Scout age Knives loomed large in my life because, like, Cub Scout kid you always had to have a knife on you, cause like, you'd use it for stuff like, kid stuff.
Scott: for some reason, people, when they're thinking about outdoorsy tools knife is always the first one.
Rym: yep, now, honestly, like a lot of that is kid nonsense.
Rym: like, I, even when we go camping I usually don't bring a knife, like, there's no point.
Scott: it's, I think, it's kid nonsense.
Scott: it's, you know, the forbidden thing is always you know, ooh, it's it's dangerous, so I want it right, yeah Bart goes on that odyssey and almost dies, all because he wanted to have a knife.
Scott: yep, exactly.
Rym: and as a kid, I used knives a lot, but I used them for Cub Scout stuff exclusively whittling, and like, cutting stuff when we were camping, with the Cub Scouts and in no other part of my life also in the kitchen?
Rym: well, kitchen knives, I do want to talk about, cause that's a different thing.
Rym: when I was a kid, I didn't think about or care about kitchen knives, there just were kitchen knives and as a kid, I kind of just picked a random one cause I didn't know better whenever I needed a knife.
Rym: now I know a lot about knives, now I care a lot about knives.
Scott: so the reason I thought about this episode right, is because actually, of not a knife, or maybe yes, a knife, if you're, I don't know how pedantic you are, but because of a scissor.
Scott: so I have this scissor, it's the Fiskars.
Scott: it's the best scissor, I've had it for a super long time.
Scott: it's the best, it's like a Fiskar like 9 in 1, right, it's like it's got like a box opener and a bottle opener, and it's like it does all this shit, but it looks just like a scissor.
Scott: but it's like this multi-use multi everything, and the thing is you can actually take the two halves of the scissor apart, and one of the sides is basically just a knife.
Scott: right, you can use it like a knife, the other side you, I guess technically is still a knife, cause it has a sharp edge, but you couldn't really use it like a knife on its own so much, because of the shape of it.
Scott: but the point is a scissor is two knives, and anyway I lost this scissor, I don't know where the fuck it is.
Scott: how could I possibly lose a giant?
Scott: you know, I still have the multi-tool that we got two of from the early days of Amazon, yeah, well yeah how could I lose a giant, you know scissor like this, it has to be in this apartment somewhere, it's not like I took it out somewhere.
Scott: it's not like it went in the garbage, I don't know where the hell is it, I need it, I use it so frequently, and I've had it so long that really, like for household doings, that's really, you know, even though only half of it is knife shaped.
Scott: when you take it apart, that half knife is basically anything that's not kitchen knifery, that's what I use, is that thing, it's like that is so functional for every day in a normal person's house, not doing you know, you know, tool-y hardware-y kind of work just household work, cutting up a box or whatever.
Scott: that's where it's at.
Rym: so I have an old like flip out utility knife, like a really short one.
Rym: it's like three inches long that we leave near the door and I just use that for opening packages.
Rym: and the only knives we really bring when we're camping and hiking, if we do bring them are, we have one like chopping kitchen knife that's designed for camping and has like a thin, like it has a case so you can bring it in your camping and that's literally just to like chop potatoes and onions when we're cooking dinner like out in the woods.
Rym: and if we need a knife to do anything other than cooking food we actually have one really nice knife that Emily heard we were doing this topic and walked in so I can show it to everybody on the screen, we have a Finnish lap knife which is just a very nice one-handed knife that is generally useful and durable and cool.
Rym: okay, that's a good knife, good style, nice and compact, good to bring in the woods.
Rym: but other than that most of my thinking about knives in my daily life is around using the correct knife in the kitchen for the correct task in the kitchen with the correct technique.
Scott: it's like if it's a bread you gotta get the serrated knife
Rym: the bread knife, or possibly a deli knife, there's a little bit of distinction there,
Scott: yeah, almost everything you're gonna be using just a chef knife, right, like an 8 inch chef knife, whatever, right, can do almost anything.
Scott: you don't really need another knife.
Scott: but you might have the santoku which has the different shape.
Rym: I find the santoku to be the most versatile useful knife like.
Rym: that's the default knife I use in the kitchen, usually use it for most of the time.
Scott: you cut something that's not a bread, you're cutting a vegetable.
Scott: you cut a meat less often I'd say, and so that's basically a vegetable chopper.
Scott: that's what it is, and so yeah, it is a very versatile knife, you know, the chef knife can do the vegetable or the meat, so it actually has more, but I guess the santoku is a little bit more specialized to the vegetable and vegetable is the thing you cut most often, so it could be good to have, I actually don't have one, but I just got two chef knives instead,
Rym: yeah, we love to see, we've got one, so we have a cleaver but we almost never use it.
Scott: because, yup, it's interesting how, like I never use a cleaver I never need one really, but there's some chefs I've seen, like especially like Chinese chefs you see on TV.
Scott: they use the cleaver for fucking everything, they got like a mega sharp cleaver and they do everything with that, just cleaver everything, garlic whether it's a garlic or a giant meat or whatever,
Rym: as a kid we didn't even have a cleaver in the house, we
Scott: didn't either,
Rym: we have a cleaver only because a relative had two by accident and they're really nice, so just gave us the other one and it's just in the kitchen, and I used, let's see, what did I use it for?
Rym: I used it once to cut a big gourd open in two like a really tough gourd, I just whacked it, and you know what, it cleaved.
Scott: it cleaved really well, yeah, that's what it's.
Scott: that's what it's really for, the problem is
Rym: cleavers, proper heavy cleavers are hard to use in any environment where you do not have a standalone butcher block, because even a thick cutting board on like a formica or a counter that isn't like thick, heavy marble or something, it's like there's a little bit of reverberation and it's like not a good feeling, you really want to use a cleaver on a full sized butcher block.
Scott: I mean, I see chefs on TV using it just on same as everything else, so maybe don't hit so hard depends on what you're cutting, I guess.
Scott: but yeah, there's several knives that you can use in the kitchen, you get your paring knives.
Scott: you got, you know, all kinds steak knives, butter knives right, which aren't really sharp, right, it's like it's funny that someone might say that a scissor is not a knife or a scissor is not two knives stuck together.
Scott: but then they'll say a butter knife is a knife even though the butter knife is dull AF.
Rym: yeah, a butter knife is just a stick just a flat stick.
Scott: how sharp does it have to be where it becomes knife and is no longer just a piece of metal?
Rym: but I guess as I got older, it was actually right around when we moved to the city like 2009, 2010 when I started to pay a lot of attention to the correct technique of using the different kinds of knives and also getting rid of old shitty knives that I just happened to own and buying a set of specific knives that I liked, that we used for specific purposes.
Rym: I got rid of almost every knife I owned because a lot of them were just like no, you could have just sharpened, right, that's the thing.
Scott: is you see these YouTube videos?
Rym: well no, a lot of them were just like crappy knives with like bad handles like they were like hand-me-downs from the family.
Rym: someone
Scott: has some crappy knife that's like from the dollar store and they sharpen it and it's amazing because they sharpened it, but the thing is if the metal it's made of is not very durable or it's not comfortable to hold or the shape of it isn't conducive to actual like the actual things you're going to be doing with it it's like yeah, it's sharp, it's going to dull quickly, right, it might even break, you know you might hurt yourself because holding it is awkward,
Rym: right, it's
Scott: like.
Scott: so when you buy a knife, you know it's like.
Scott: of course when you buy a new knife if it's a high quality one it's going to start off mega sharp because they don't sell you a dull one, that would be foolish right, but you're really buying, what's the quality of, you know, the steel or ceramic or whatever it's made of, right
Rym: quality of the blade and comfort of the handle, yeah,
Scott: how does it feel?
Scott: what shape is it, is it good at its function?
Scott: and then the sharpening is going to be on you because even if you buy the world's most expensive, bestest, amazing knife you have to sharpen it, yep it's going to go dull, that's just how physics works,
Rym: and that's something as I got into my thirties I started paying more attention to is the care of good knives because they're if you're like us you cook a lot, like cooking is one of the things you do often in your life.
Rym: so I feel like it's very much worth it to have a good set of tools to do cooking with, cooking with crappy tools is uncomfortable difficult, and as Scott noted sometimes dangerous, a dull knife is way more dangerous than a sharp knife, that's not just a thing.
Rym: knife people say, dull knives are dangerous to use.
Scott: right, a dull knife, you're pushing hard on it and then when it finally breaks through if it breaks through, it goes duh, right and that sudden uh could mean some slippage and then some cutting yourself.
Scott: or who knows, but if you have a sharp knife it just slides through with no resistance and you just go shucka, shucka, shucka, shucka and you just keep your hand away from the sharp part and you won't be cut by the sharp knife.
Scott: right, any knife is gonna cut you no matter how dull or sharp if you put your hand in the wrong spot.
Scott: so the danger is our likelihood of cutting yourself when you don't do something foolish.
Rym: and I'm not gonna try to explain the technique one, cause we're not experts into.
Scott: you can watch a YouTube video find a YouTube video of chefs using knives and like find good ones, there's 10 bajillion videos on YouTube of how to sharpen a knife how to buy a knife, which knife to get what knife is for what and how to use them.
Scott: so there's no reason for us to talk about it.
Scott: that
Rym: will enrich your life, I highly recommend learning how to use the knives that you have and use in the kitchen and learning the good techniques and making them second nature, like I don't have to think about it when I use a knife and I'm just not gonna cut myself because I'm using the techniques that professionals use and I taught myself that and I practice that,
Scott: so the one thing though that you do want to be aware of is the difference between sharpening and honing.
Scott: people don't know this, they see that you know that stick and they see the chef's like rubbing the knife on the stick, like ching ching ching.
Scott: right, that's honing.
Scott: what you're doing when you hone is you're not sharpening the knife at all.
Scott: it's that the very edge of the blade might be like, you know not straight, if you look at it with like a microscope you'll see it might be warbly or bent to one side, right, and if you just straighten it out to make all the sharp part, you know, in line with itself, right, that's what honing does and you should hone, basically every time you use the knife or almost every other time frequently, that's why you see chefs doing it a lot.
Scott: but that doesn't sharpen the knife, it's still gonna go dull and honing it, no matter how much you hone it, it's just gonna make it straight and dull, sharpening.
Scott: you actually remove material from the knife to make it pointier and, you know, watch YouTube videos on how to do that, there's several different ways.
Scott: you can use some stones, you could use an electric sharpener, it really doesn't matter which way, there's.
Scott: obviously there are differences, but you're just a normal person and not a professional chef, so just sharpen it, and you know what sharpen all the other knives you use out of the kitchen as well.
Scott: right, if you've got a multi-tool if you've got a scissor, the scissor I mentioned has a sharpener that comes with it.
Scott: it's just a little white stick that's like built into the cover, and you rub the two halves of the scissor.
Scott: you know, in these slots that are lined up to sharpen the halves of the scissor, and you know what, using if you've used a dull scissor like some kids safety scissors, you'll see the value in sharp scissors.
Rym: and, well I mean, there's a reason why, if any of you don't know about this stuff.
Rym: so, if you know anyone who has fabric scissors if they see you cutting paper with fabric scissors, they might kill you because that's gonna mess those scissors up real quick.
Rym: but, fabric scissors like well sharpened scissors you know when you watch someone who seems like they know what they're doing, like wrapping gifts or like cutting fabric, and they don't even cut, cut, cut, cut, cut, they just kind of slide the scissor and everything just cuts.
Rym: that's what good scissors can do.
Scott: that's right.
Scott: it also depends on what you're cutting, not everything you cut can be cut that way.
Rym: yeah, now the people I'm suspicious of, are the people who talk a lot about their daily carry, that's a term that's mostly used by weirdos who carry guns around, weirdos who carry knives around, for purposes other than whittling wood, or camping like, the person who goes to a convention,
Scott: anything that's tactical, that looks like a military tries to look like it's something that a military person is supposed to have even though they don't.
Rym: you can recognize these people in the wild, because they have a knife in their pocket to go to something like a gaming convention, or a store and if they're told they cannot bring their knife into a place they get weird and mad about it and start talking about how technically it's legal to carry this knife, one, just avoid those
Scott: people, it's the right number of inches
Rym: like, you don't need a knife 99% of the time.
Scott: that's what I'm saying, there's this sort of fallacy of these people who you know, it's obvious they just want to have a weapon, right, because it makes them feel big because they're small.
Scott: same thing with guns, just on a smaller level you know, and it's like, hey is the knife really?
Scott: how often do you really use it?
Scott: how often do you really have scenarios where you need to use it?
Scott: you know, like I have this multi-tool and for a lot, I carried, when I was going to an office every day, I just had this in my messenger bag all the time.
Scott: and when did I use this?
Scott: actually, most days I carried it home and carried it back, and when I did have to use it, how often was it the knife that was being used?
Scott: no, more often it was the scissor, the screwdriver.
Rym: you know what I used that in my multi-tool, 90% of the time I was using the screwdriver in it, and the other 10% of the time I was using the pliers that it turns into.
Scott: I think I used the ruler more than I used the knife part, right, it's like.
Scott: you know, in normal everyday life, unless you're, I don't know a jungle guide with like a machete, or a knifesmith, it's like there's only certain professions, right, where a knife is actually getting used a chef, with frequency normal people doing office-y shit, or you know, retail, or whatever you're carrying around the knife, that you're just carrying around the knife because you're that kind of guy and
Rym: you know
Scott: what, it's always a guy.
Scott: right, the ladies are a character.
Rym: if you've got a crude little kind of job, where you're cracking packs like opening boxes, or breaking down boxes there's a tool you may have heard of called a box cutter, that is the right tool for that job.
Scott: that's right, that is also a kind of knife.
Scott: it is a kind of knife, but it also doesn't need to be sharpened, because you can just pop out another blade and snap the other one off, yup, you also don't need much.
Scott: does a razor count as a knife?
Scott: ahh, if I'm shaving, we don't need to talk about shaving because we've got an old episode about that.
Rym: what if I put a razor blade in a hot dog?
Rym: is that a sandwich or a knife?
Scott: yeah, if I take the hot dog with a razor blade in it, and I can swing it around and try to cut things at what point do you cross the line between knife, short sword?
Scott: alright, other sword?
Rym: oh, well that's easy, knives do 1d4 damage while short swords do 1d6 damage?
Scott: who knows if they've changed the rules on us?
Rym: yeah, fuck if I know, you know what when I play Baldur's Gate, I just look at damage first, like I don't know how much damage my weapons do, I don't actually care that much.
Rym: I know what damage weapons did in like 2nd ed D&D.
Scott: yeah, it's like, does it even have to be made of metal?
Scott: I could get a wooden knife link at the start of his adventure with his little wood sword, yup, that is not a wooden sword.
Scott: if you sharpen anything that's hard, and won't break, you can cut things with it, and if it's in a handy shape that's a knife, right, it doesn't have to be metal.
Rym: how many of you have been in the situation when you're in elementary school and you've got a candy cane, you're sucking on that candy cane, and you never bite the tip off, and eventually it turns into a dangerous stiletto, and then you poke yourself with it because you find out that it's actually sharp and dangerous?
Scott: yeah, I mean, you know, paper cuts ceramic knives you could take stone and sharpen it, right, stone age.
Rym: so, you know, actually, you know what the hard difficult question to answer would be would a stiletto count as a knife?
Rym: because it's sharp, but only at the very, very, it's a piercing pokey one, but not a slashy slashy one, Dungeons and Dragons classes that as a completely different kind of weapon and a completely different kind of damage.
Rym: piercing, slashing, bludgeoning.
Rym: butter knives do bludgeoning damage, I'd argue, I agree I guess, but you could.
Scott: if you pushed hard enough, you could pierce.
Rym: I mean, if you push hard enough anything could cut anything, I guess not.
Scott: if it's too wide, a butter knife is narrow, right, and hard.
Scott: it's still narrow and hard, so you can pierce things with it as long as you have enough force and the thing you're trying to pierce isn't harder than the butter knife.
Rym: the case in point all of that does not matter to your normal life, so don't be that guy who carries a knife around all the time and talks about his daily carry, you just weird everybody else out, and carry a knife when you have a practical reason to carry one, 99% of that is because you are camping.
Scott: who knows, someone out there might have an actual job where they're knifing in which
Rym: case
Scott: you should have a knife that is appropriate to the job you're doing and not, you know, tactical knife, because I guarantee you, anyone listening to this, your job is not tactical combat, and you know
Rym: what, if your job is tactical combat I would be interested in hearing about it because I still suspect, even in that case, the knife is not exactly the go-to or the most important thing in your job.
Scott: And even if it is, it's not the knife that is actually useful and best, I would really imagine is not the knife that the knife nerds are buying
Rym: on,
Scott: you know, they're making YouTube videos, I would imagine it is a different knife that the actual tactical combat people are using.
Scott: Yup.
Rym: But at least in your kitchen, like the moral of this one is this is one of those rights of adulthood or rights of someone who just makes their life better.
Rym: If you cook a lot, learn about the knives you use in the kitchen and get appropriate knives and take care of them.
Rym: That will make your life better in ways you don't realize, it'll just make a task you do often much more pleasant, much more comfortable and you'll be better at it and you're less likely to cut the tip of your finger off like I did back in the year 2007 was when I cut the tip of my finger
Scott: off.
Scott: Unlike other dangerous tools that exist in the world, right, that have say a more limited set of real practical uses, everyone basically is going to encounter knife, right, in their lives and have to use knife to do various tasks.
Scott: And so, not being afraid of knife, learning about them at least some minimal extent, knowing how to sharpen them or at least knowing that they need to be sharpened and knowing how to use them safely can prevent trips to the emergency room.
Scott: Knives send a lot of people to the emergency room every year and you can avoid being one of those people and you can accomplish tasks efficiently in life without fear by purchasing the correct knives and using them in the correct manner.
Rym: I actually remember something I haven't thought about in a long time When you cut your finger?
Rym: Oh no no, I mean that I think about often because the scar is still there, like you can see the line where the tip of my finger was completely cut off and I can't feel anything in the tip of that finger.
Scott: Good job.
Rym: Yeah, but no, not that.
Rym: So I briefly, in college, dated someone who actually knew how to knife fight for real and had taken classes and learned this because this person's mother was a private investigator who needed to know about that because being a PI is actually kind of a really dangerous job and there's a whole side story I'm not going to get into, but I was curious and taught me and I learned a little bit about how knife fights actually work in the real world from someone who knew what they were talking about.
Rym: and if I had to summarize everything I learned the moral of knife fighting is never ever ever get in a knife fight.
Rym: Everyone involved in a knife fight, but everyone involved in any knife fight gets cut badly.
Rym: There is no universe where you are in a knife fight and you are not cut even if you win.
Rym: Knife fights are the worst possible fights.
Scott: I imagine that even if you're in a knife fight and you're the only one with a knife, you have a knife and they don't, you probably still get cut badly.
Rym: Yeah, actually.
Scott: As long as the other person can fight back and they're not, for example, tied up or something.
Scott: In fact, to almost quote exactly, the number of people In which case it's not really a knife fight, it's more just of a knife torture or a knife assault.
Rym: The number of people who will get cut badly in a knife fight is n+1 n being the number of knives involved in the fight.
Scott: Well, it could be.
Scott: I think it's just, you know, if there's one knife and like five people I could imagine all six people getting cut.
Rym: I mean, basically if there's a knife in a room where violence is happening, I feel like a lot of people are going to get cut, regardless if the knife is even used in the fight.
Scott: Right.
Rym: Anyway, you know a movie where you see like an action hero holding a knife backwards, a lot of people like saw that in a movie once and think oh, that's a good way to cut your arm open.
Rym: That's a good way to get cut.
Rym: But you know you see like two people having a knife fight in a movie and the knives are hitting each other a bunch like it's a sword fight.
Rym: The way knife fights that actually happen in the real world were described to me, and I got to see some footage of like security camera footage of knife fights that are involved in investigations.
Rym: Imagine the opposite of that.
Rym: Almost every time the knife moves, it cuts someone.
Rym: It's not like you think in the movies.
Rym: Knife fights are real bad.
Rym: No.
Scott: And you know, it's like Rym cut his finger a tiny bit in the kitchen.
Rym: That was a traumatic emergency room stitches like big problem.
Scott: Right.
Scott: And in the knife fight you're going to, everyone will suffer several such cuts at minimum.
Scott: One is bad enough.
Scott: It's like imagine being there in the emergency room with like three or seven or and big or it's like no, don't don't mess it.
Scott: Don't do it.
Scott: Just run.
Scott: If there's a knife fight, run.
Scott: If you're far away from the knife, it can't cut you.
Rym: Don't do what Donnie Don't does.
Scott: And knife throwers, almost no one is any good at that.
Scott: Don't worry if they if I'm not too afraid of someone throwing a knife at me if I'm running and I'm far enough away.
Scott: Yeah.
Scott: That's I'm not saying I want that to happen.
Scott: I'm saying that's that's preferable to being close and then trying to slash me with it.
Scott: Right.
Scott: If it's like if I'm choosing to dodge a throw knife or deal with a close rein, it's like, no, get the fuck away from that knife.
Rym: This has been GeekNights with Rym and Scott.
Rym: Special thanks to DJ Pretzel for the opening theme.
Scott: Be sure to visit our website at frontrowcrew.com for show notes, discussion, links and more.
Rym: Remember, GeekNights is not one but four different shows.
Rym: Mondays are science and technology.
Rym: Tuesdays, gaming and games.
Rym: Wednesdays are animation and comics.
Rym: Thursdays are arbitrary and indiscriminate.
Rym: GeekNights is distributed under a creative comments attribution 4.0 international license.
Scott: GeekNights is recorded live with no studio and no audience.
Scott: But unlike those other late shows, it's actually recorded at night.
Rym: And the Patreon patrons for this episode of GeekNights are Ellen Joyce, Linki G, Dread Lily, Tana Brake, K.S.K, K.A.R.E,
Rym: M.I.X.F.U.S.I.D.D.,
Rym: Christopher
Rym: W.R.E.C.H.,
Rym: Malton Finn, Joel Hayes, Penny Reimer, Rebecca Dunn, Sam Erickson, Sherman Von Horrell and a bunch of people who do not want me to say their names.
Rym: We're back from PAX, mostly back to normal on our schedules.
Rym: And tonight, I leave you only with.